and how to find their way to their old nesting grounds and feeding grounds. There were some conservationists, really famous conservationists like Stanley Temple, who is one of the founders of conservation biology, and Kate Jones from the IUCN, which does the Red List. They're excited about all this, but they're also concerned that it might be competitive with the extremely important efforts to protect endangered species that are still alive, that haven't gone extinct yet. You see, you want to work on protecting the animals out there. You want to work on getting the market for ivory in Asia down so you're not using 25,000 elephants a year. But at the same time, conservation biologists are realizing that bad news bums people out. And so the Red List is really important, keep track of what's endangered and critically endangered, and so on. But they're about to create what they call a Green List, and the Green List will have species that are doing fine, thank you, species that were endangered, like the bald eagle, but they're much better off now, thanks to everybody's good work, and protected areas around the world that are very, very well managed. So basically, they're learning how to build on good news. And they see reviving extinct species as the kind of good news you might be able to build on. Here's a couple related examples. Captive breeding will be a major part of bringing back these species. The California condor was down to 22 birds in 1987. Everybody thought is was finished. Thanks to captive breeding at the San Diego Zoo, there's 405 of them now, 226 are out in the wild. That technology will be used on de-extincted animals. Another success story is the mountain gorilla in Central Africa. In 1981, Dian Fossey was sure they were going extinct. There were just 254 left. Now there are 880. They're increasing in population by three percent a year. The secret is, they have an eco-tourism program, which is absolutely brilliant. So this photograph was taken last month by Ryan with an iPhone. That's how comfortable these wild gorillas are with visitors. Another interesting project, though it's going to need some help, is the northern white rhinoceros. There's no breeding pairs left. But this is the kind of thing that a wide variety of DNA for this animal is available in the frozen zoo. A bit of cloning, you can get them back. So where do we go from here? These have been private meetings so far. I think it's time for the subject to go public. What do people think about it? You know, do you want extinct species back? Do you want extinct species back? (Applause) Tinker Bell is going to come fluttering down. It is a Tinker Bell moment, because what are people excited about with this? What are they concerned about? We're also going to push ahead with the passenger pigeon. So Ben Novak, even as we speak, is joining the group that Beth Shapiro has at UC Santa Cruz. They're going to work on the genomes of the passenger pigeon and the band-tailed pigeon. As that data matures, they'll send it to George Church, who will work his magic, get passenger pigeon DNA out of that. We'll get help from Bob Lanza and Mike McGrew to get that into germ plasm that can go into chickens that can produce passenger pigeon squabs that can be raised by band-tailed pigeon parents, and then from then on, it's passenger pigeons all the way, maybe for the next six million years. You can do the same thing, as the costs come down, for the Carolina parakeet, for the great auk, for the heath hen, for the ivory-billed woodpecker, for the Eskimo curlew, for the Caribbean monk seal, for the woolly mammoth. Because the fact is, humans have made a huge hole in nature in the last 10,000 years. We have the ability now, and maybe the moral obligation, to repair some of the damage. Most of that we'll do by expanding and protecting wildlands, by expanding and protecting the populations of endangered species. But some species that we killed off totally we could consider bringing back to a world that misses them. Thank you. (Applause) Chris Anderson: Thank you. I've got a question. So, this is an emotional topic. Some people stand. I suspect there are some people out there sitting, kind of asking tormented questions, almost, about, well, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait a minute, there's something wrong with mankind interfering in nature in this way. There's going to be unintended consequences. You're going to uncork some sort of Pandora's box of who-knows-what. Do they have a point? Stewart Brand: Well, the earlier point is we interfered in a big way by making these animals go extinct, and many of them were keystone species, and we changed the whole ecosystem they were in by letting them go. Now, there's the shifting baseline problem, which is, so when these things come back, they might replace some birds that are there that people really know and love. I think that's, you know, part of how it'll work. This is a long, slow process -- One of the things I like about it, it's multi-generation. We will get woolly mammoths back. CA: Well it feels like both the conversation and the potential here are pretty thrilling. Thank you so much for presenting. SB: Thank you. CA: Thank you. (Applause)
y cómo volver a asentarse en sus antiguas áreas de nidificación y de alimentación. Había algunos conservacionistas, muy famosos, como Stanley Temple, que es uno de los fundadores de la biología conservacionista, y Kate Jones de UICN, que publica la Lista Roja. Están muy entusiasmados con todo esto, pero también están preocupados de que pueda entrar en competencia con los enormes esfuerzos para proteger especies en peligro de extinción que aún están vivas, y que todavía no se han extinguido. Verán, se quiere trabajar en proteger los animales que existen. Se quiere trabajar en bajar la demanda de marfil en el mercado asiático, para no matar 25 000 elefantes al año. Pero al mismo tiempo, los biólogos conservacionistas notan que las malas noticias deprimen a la gente. Así que la Lista Roja es muy importante, para llevar registro de qué está en peligro de extinción y en peligro crítico de extinción, etc. Pero están por crear lo que llaman una Lista Verde, y la Lista Verde, enumerará a las especies que están bien, gracias, especies que solían estar en peligro de extinción, como el águila calva, pero que ahora están mucho mejor, gracias al buen trabajo de todos, y a las áreas de protección de todo el mundo que están muy, muy bien dirigidas. Así que básicamente, están aprendiendo a redactar buenas noticias. Y ven que revivir especies extintas es el tipo de buena noticia a partir de la que se puede construir. Les doy un par de ejemplos relacionados. La crianza en cautiverio será una parte importante de traer a la vida a estas especies. El cóndor de California se vio reducido a 22 aves en 1987. Todos pensaron que estaba acabado. Gracias a la crianza en cautiverio en el Zoológico de San Diego, actualmente hay 405 de ellos, 226 están en su hábitat natural. Esa tecnología será utilizada con los animales de-extintos. Otra historia exitosa es la del gorila de montaña en África Central. En 1981, Dian Fossey estaba segura de que se extinguirían. Quedaban tan solo 254 ejemplares. Hoy hay 880. Y su población aumenta un 3% por año. El secreto es que tienen un programa de eco turismo, que es absolutamente brillante. Esta fotografía la tomó Ryan el mes pasado con un iPhone. Así de cómodos se sienten estos gorilas salvajes con los visitantes. Otro proyecto interesante, aunque necesitará algo de ayuda, es el del rinoceronte blanco del norte. No quedan pares de reproducción. Pero esta es la clase de situaciones para las cuales existe una gran variedad de ADN disponible en el zoo congelado. Un poco de clonación y se les puede traer de vuelta. Ahora, ¿cuál es el siguiente paso? Estas han sido conferencias privadas hasta ahora. Creo que es hora de que el tema se haga público. ¿Qué piensa la gente al respecto? Ya saben, ¿quieren que vuelvan las especies extintas? ¿Quieren que vuelvan las especies extintas? (Aplausos) Campanita vendrá volando ahora. Es un momento para Campanita, porque, ¿qué es lo que entusiasma a la gente de este tema? ¿Qué les preocupa? Vamos a seguir adelante con la paloma migratoria. Así que Ben Novak, en este momento, está sumándose al grupo que Beth Shapiro tiene en UC Santa Cruz. Van a trabajar en el genoma de la paloma migratoria y la paloma de collar. A medida que esta información crezca, se la enviarán a George Church, quien operará su magia, y de eso, sacará ADN de paloma migratoria. Obtendremos la ayuda de Bob Lanza y Mike McGraw para introducir el plasma germinal en gallinas para que reproduzcan polluelos de paloma migratoria, que puedan ser criados por padres palomas de collar, y a partir de este momento, serán palomas migratorias para siempre, quizás durante los próximos seis millones de años. Ustedes pueden hacer lo mismo, a medida que bajen los costes, por la cotorra de Carolina, el alca gigante, por el urogallo grande, el carpintero real, por el zarapito esquimal, la foca monje del Caribe, y por el mamut lanudo. Porque el hecho es que, los humanos hemos creado un enorme agujero en la naturaleza, durante los últimos 10 000 años. Hoy tenemos la capacidad, y quizá la obligación moral, de reparar un poco del daño. Mucho de esto lo lograremos expandiendo y protegiendo las tierras salvajes, expandiendo y protegiendo las poblaciones de especies en peligro de extinción. Pero a algunas especies que hemos matado por completo podríamos considerar traerlas a la vida nuevamente a un mundo que las echa de menos. Gracias. (Aplausos) Chris Anderson: Gracias. Tengo una pregunta. Este es un tema emotivo. Algunos están de pie. Sospecho que debe de haber algunos sentados en la audiencia atormentándose con preguntas del estilo: bien, espera, espera, espera, espera un minuto, hay algo que está muy mal si la humanidad interfiere con la naturaleza de esta forma. Va a haber consecuencias no intencionadas. Se va a abrir una especie de Caja de Pandora de quién sabe qué. ¿Tienen algo de razón? Stewart Brand: Bien, el primer punto es que interferimos muchísimo cuando hicimos que estos animales se extinguieran, y muchos eran especies claves, y cambiamos todo el ecosistema del que eran parte cuando los dejamos ir. Ahora, tenemos el problema de los puntos de referencia cambiantes, que es que cuando estas especies regresen, pueden llegar a reemplazar algunas aves que las personas ya conocen y aman. Y creo que eso, ya saben, es parte de como sucederá. Este es un proceso largo y lento a la vez. Una de las cosas que me gustan de esto es que es multigeneracional. Traeremos de vuelta a los mamuts lanudos. CA: Bien, pare que tanto la conversación, como el potencial aquí, son muy emocionantes. Muchísimas gracias por la presentación. SB: Gracias. CA: Gracias. (Aplausos)